

BIOINFORMATICIAN II

Respiratory Diseases Laboratory Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, USA

☑ jhamlin@cdc.gov | ☑ jennahamlin

I am a scientist with 10+ years of experience in classical genetics, genomics, and evolutionary biology. My training includes using a range of tools - bioinformatics, population genetics, molecular evolution all with experimental design in mind. Over the years as my computational skills increased, the genomes of the organisms I work on have gotten smaller. Now, I work at the interface of public health, application development, and understanding organisms that can cause harm to humans with an empahsis of developing reproduciable research.

Education

University of Georgia Athens, GA

Ph.D. IN GENETICS 2015

University of North Carolina - Asheville

Asheville, NC

B.S. IN BIOLOGY

2010

Appointments

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Contractor with ASRT Inc.

Atlanta, GA

BIOINFORMATICIAN II WITH DIVISION OF BACTERIAL DISEASES

November 2020 - Current

- * Interfacing with state public health laboratories (PHL)
 - Communicated with members of state PHL to provide guidenance regarding bionformatics and genomics for Legionella species
- * Refactored Legionella Species ID tool for broader compatibility and interfacing with Nextflow Tower
 - Removed structural design issues in original code that prevented expansion and adding of new functionalities
- * Development of method validation plan for Legionella Species ID tool
 - Researched and proposed statistically sound validation plan for tool that uses next generation sequencing data
- * Phylogenetic and phylodynamic analyses for Legionella isolates of public health concern
 - Performing analyses and generating statistical summaries and visualizations
 - Writing and editing manuscripts for publication
 - Identifying scientific questions answerable with existing data
- * Developing or testing scripts and pipelines as necessary
 - Generated script to interact with National Center of Biotechnology Information for downloading all available Legionella genomes
 - Evaluated using Nextflow pipeline for mapping Legionella genomes
- * 60-day detail on Data Analytics and Visualization for Vaccine Task Force (April June 2021)
 - Produced weekly reports and consolidated steps for document creation to be reproducible via one script

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; Fellow with APHL

Atlanta, GA

ASSOCIATION OF PUBLIC HEALTH LABORATORIES (APHL) BIOINFORMATICS FELLOW

September 2019 - November 2020

- * Developing tinselR an Rshiny application for annotating outbreak trees
 - tinselR is an open-source downloadable package in the R language used for phylogenetic tree analysis and visualization
- * Participated in APHL core competency and leadership training
 - Gained skills and knowledge for a career in public health
- * 30-day detail on Routine Reporting for COVID-19 Response (June July 2020)
 - Produced daily and weekly reports for task force. Consolidated steps for document creation to be reproducible via one script

University of Georgia (UGA)

Athens, GA

BENSASSON LAB POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

October 2017 - August 2019

- * Directed collaborative research with UGA graduate and undergraduate students
- * Collated and streamlined genome mapping for 1000 Saccharomyces cerevisiae isolates as lab resource
- * Used iterative approach to assign 400 genomes to well-defined populations using best practices for population genomics and phylogenetics
- * Resolved haplotypes for Candida albicans genomes with PacBio sequencing

Indiana University (IU)

Bloomington, IN

Moyle Lab Post-Doctoral Researcher

June 2015 - September 2017

- * Directed research with faculty, graduate, and undergraduates at IU and with two external universities
- * Genome-wide study of factors that determine the likelihood of introgression for Solanum species
- * Streamlined genotyping to generate biological replicates. Validate data accuracy using technical replicates along with statistical analyses
- * Identified targeting rates and floral trait differences with biological & technical replicates in large-scale crossing project via statistical analyses

FEBRUARY 2022 JENNA HAMLIN · CURRICULUM VITAE



Analytical

DATA SCIENCE, EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN, NEXT GENERATION SEQUENCING, GENOMICS, HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING,

PROJECT MANAGEMENT, QUALITY CONTROL, REPRODUCIBLE RESEARCH, STATISTICS, TECHNICAL WRITING AND

DOCUMENTATION

Programming

AWK - PROFICIENT, BASH - EXPERT, PYTHON - EXPERT, R - EXPERT, RMARKDOWN - EXPERT, NEXTFLOW - PROFICIENT, GITHUB -

EXPERT

SPECIES

Publications.

JAP Hamlin, T Nakov, A Williams-Newkirk

Announcements

Microbiology Resource

 ${\tt TINSELR-AN\ R\ Shiny\ Application\ for\ Annotating\ Phylogenetic\ Trees}$

Evolution letters

ASSESSING BIOLOGICAL FACTORS AFFECTING POSTSPECIATION INTROGRESSION

2020

JAP Hamlin, GB Dias, CM Bergman, D Bensasson

G3

Phased Diploid Genome Assemblies for Three Strains of Candida albicans from Oak Trees

2019

TWO LOCI CONTRIBUTE EPISTASTICALLY TO HETEROSPECIFIC POLLEN REJECTION, A POSTMATING ISOLATING BARRIER BETWEEN

G3 2017

JAP Hamlin, TJ Simmonds, ML Arnold

JAP Hamlin, MS Hibbins, LC Moyle

JAP Hamlin, NA Sherman, LC Moyle

Biological Journal of the Linnean

Society

2017

NICHE CONSERVATISM FOR ECOLOGICAL PREFERENCE IN THE LOUISIANA IRIS SPECIES COMPLEX

Journal of Heredity

NEUTRAL AND SELECTIVE PROCESSES DRIVE POPULATION DIFFERENTIATION FOR IRIS HEXAGONA

2015

ML Arnold, AN Brothers, JAP Hamlin, SJ Taylor, NH Martin

Reticulate evolution

DIVERGENCE-WITH-GENE-FLOW—WHAT HUMANS AND OTHER MAMMALS GOT UP TO

201.

JAP Hamlin, ML Arnold

Determining Population Structure and Hybridization for Two Iris Species.

Ecology and Evolution

ML Arnold, JAP Hamlin, AN Brothers, ES Ballerini, RS Singh, J Xu, ...

ML Arnold, ES Ballerini, AN Brothers, JAP Hamlin, CDA Ishibashi, ...

Rapidly evolving genes and genetic

systems

NATURAL HYBRIDIZATION AS A CATALYST OF RAPID EVOLUTIONARY CHANGE

Plant Ecology & Diversity

THE GENOMICS OF NATURAL SELECTION AND ADAPTATION: CHRISTMAS PAST, PRESENT AND FUTURE (?).

2011

Presentations

JAP Hamlin, ML Arnold

Talks

tinselR - An RShiny App for Phylogenetic Tree Annotation.

Atlanta, GA

CDC DATA VIZ DAY

2020

Start Writing Manuscripts in Rmarkdown.

Atlanta, GA

GENOMICS INTEREST GROUP - TECHINCAL

Build Shiny Apps.

Athens, GA

Warnell School of Forestry & Natural Resources Data Manipulation and Management course

Athens, GA

2018

2018

Population Genomics of wild and domesticated yeast.University of Georgia Enthusiasts of Diversity Genetics and Evolution

_---

No Easy D: Little Evidence for Introgression from Whole-Genome Data in Wild Solanum.

Portland, OR

SOCIETY FOR THE STUDY OF EVOLUTION

Epistasis for Postmating Prezygotic Isolation. Austin, TX SOCIETY FOR THE STUDY OF EVOLUTION 2016 Spatial, temporal, and genome-wide patterns of differentiation for the Louisiana iris Bloomington, IN species complex. Indiana Unviversity Brown Bag What Drives Phenotypic and Genetic Divergence for Iris hexagona? Raleigh, NC SOCIETY FOR THE STUDY OF EVOLUTION 2014 Comparative Phylogeography of Two Louisiana Irises. Snowbird, UT SOCIETY FOR THE STUDY OF EVOLUTION 2013 **Posters** Tinsel - an Rshiny app for phylogenetic tree annotation. Virtual ASSOCIATION OF PUBLIC HEALTH LABORATORIES ANNUAL MEETING 2020 Tinsel - an Rshiny application for annotating outbreak trees. Canceled - Atlanta, GA INTEGRATED FOODBORNE OUTBREAK RESPONSE AND MANAGEMENT Genetic admixture and the origins of clinical Saccharomyces cerevisiae yeast. Pacific Grove, CA FUNGAL GENETICS CONFERENCE 2019 Clinical Saccharomyces cerevisiae are admixed domesticated yeast. Holderness, NH CELLULAR AND MOLECULAR FUNGAL BIOLOGY: GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCE Higher Prevalence of Genetic Exchange Given Geographic Proximity. Laural Hill, NC SOUTHEASTERN POPULATION ECOLOGY & EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS. 2017 Two Loci Contribute Epistastically to Heterospecific Pollen Tube Rejection, a Postmating Davis, CA **Isolating Barrier Between Species.** SOLANACEAE CONFERENCE 2016 What Drives Phenotypic and Genetic Divergence for Iris hexagona? Boise, ID BOTANICAL SOCIETY OF AMERICA 2014 Comparative Phylogeography of Two Louisiana Iris Species: Iris fulva and Iris Guanajuato, Mexico brevicaulis. AMERICAN GENETIC ASSOCIATION

R-Packages ____

tinselR - An R package for visulizing and annotating phylogenetic trees

https://github.com/jennahamlin/tinselR

AUTHOR AND MAINTAINER 2019

mashwrapper - a Python tool for parsing mash results

https://github.com/jennahamlin/mashwrapper

Author and maintainer 2022

Mentoring.

University of Georgia graduate students

- E. Scopel Ferreira Da Costa
- J. Pena

University of Georgia undergraduate students

- T. Simmonds
- K. Miller
- J. Foley
- S. Duque
- B. Webb

FEBRUARY 2022

Indiana University graduate students

- C. Jewell
- M. Gibson

Indiana University undergraduate students

- A. Huh
- J. Breisch
- S. Henderson
- L. Howser
- C. Plasterer
- D. Shukla
- S. Seo